the following content is provided under
a Creative Commons license your support
will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
offer high quality educational resources
for free
to make a donation or view additional
materials from hundreds of MIT courses
visit MIT opencourseware at ocw.mit.edu
last time we were talking about binary
search and I sort of left a promise to
you which I need to pick up I want to
remind you we're talking about search
which is a very fundamental thing that
we do in a whole lot of applications we
want to go find things in some data set
and I'll remind you that we sort of
separated out two cases we said if we
had an ordered list we could use binary
search and we said that was logarithmic
took log n time where n is the size of
the list if it was an unordered list we
were basically stuck with linear search
got to walk through the whole list to
see if the things there so that was a
border ant and then one of the things
that I suggested was that if we could
figure out some way to order it and in
particular if we could order it in n log
n time and we still haven't done that
but if we could do that then we said the
complexity changed a little bit but
changed in a way that I want to remind
you and the change was that in this case
if I'm doing a single search I've got a
choice I could still do the linear case
which is order n or I could say look
take the list let's sort it and then
search it but in that case we said well
to sort it was going to take n log n
time assuming I can do that once I have
it sorted I can search it in log n time
but that still isn't as good as just
doing n and this led to this idea of
amortization
which is I need to not only factor in
the cost but how am I going to use it
and typically I'm not going to just
search once in a list I'm going to
search multiple times so if I have to do
K searches and in the linear case I got
to do order and things K times its order
KN whereas in the ordered case I need to
get them sorted just still n log n but
then the search is only log n and I need
to do K of those and we suggested well
this is better than that this is
certainly better than that n plus k all
times log n is in general going to be
much better than K times n depends on N
and K but obviously as n gets big that
one's going to be better and that's just
a way of reminding you that we want to
think carefully about what are the
things we're trying to measure when we
talk about complexity here it's both the
size of the thing and how often I'm
going to use it and there's some
trade-offs but I still haven't said how
am I going to get an N log n sorting
algorithm and that's what I want to do
today one of the two things I want to do
today to set the stage for this let's go
back just for a second to binary search
the end of the lecture I said binary
search was an example of a divide and
conquer algorithm sort of an Attila the
Hun kind of approach to doing things if
you like so let me say this why I could
have made a really bad political joke
there which I will forego right so let's
say what this actually means dividing
conquer
fighting Congress says basically do the
following split the problem into several
sub problems of the same type
I'll come back in a second to help
binary search matches in that but that's
what we're going to do for each of those
subproblems I'm going to solve them
independently and then we're going to
combine those solutions and it's called
divide and conquer for the obvious
reason I'm going to divide it up into
subproblems
with the hope that those subproblems get
easier going to be easier to conquer if
you like and then I'm going to merge
them back now in the binary search case
in some sense this was a little bit
trivial
what would trivial bright trivial but
what was the divide the divide was
breaking a big search up into a half a
search we actually threw half of the
list away and we kept dividing it down
until ultimately we got something of
size-12 search that's really easy the
combination was also sort of trivial in
this case because the solution to the
sub-problem was in fact the solution to
the larger problem okay but there's the
idea of divide and conquer I'm going to
use exactly that same idea to tackle
sort again I got an unloaded list of n
elements I want to sort it into a
obviously into a sorted list in that
particular algorithm he's actually a
really nice algorithm called merge sort
and it's actually a fairly old algorithm
it was invented in 1945 by John von
Neumann other pioneers of computer
science and here's the idea behind merge
sort
I actually want to come into Anna back
into it in a funny way let's assume that
I could somehow get to the stage where
I've got two sorted lists how hard does
it work or how much work do I have to do
to actually merge them together alright
so let me give you an example suppose I
want to merge two lists and they're
sorted
just to give you an example here's one
list all right 3 12 17 24 god bless you
here's another list 1 2 4 30 haven't
said how I'm going to get those sorted
list but imagine I had two sorted lists
like that how hard is it to merge them
well it's pretty easy right I start at
the beginning of each list and I say is
1 less than 3 sure so that says one
should be the first element in my merge
list now compare the first element in
each of these lists 2 is less than 3
so 2 ought to be the next element of the
list and you get the idea what do I do
next I going to compare 3 against 4 3 is
the smallest one and I'm going to
compare 4 against 12 just going to give
me 4 and then what do I have to do 12
against 30 12 is smaller take that out
17 against 30 24 against 30 and by this
stage I got nothing left in this woman
so I just add the rest of that list in
wow I can sort to lift so I can merge
two lists I said it poorly what's the
point how many operations did it take me
to do this 7 comparisons right I got 8
elements it took me 7 comparisons
because I can take advantage of the fact
I know I only ever have to look at the
first element of each sub list those are
the only things I need to compare and
when I run out of one list I just add
the rest of the list in okay what's the
order complexity of merging I heard it
somewhere very quietly sorry and thank
you linear absolutely right and what's n
by the way here
what's it measuring
in both lists right so this is linear
order n and n is the sum of the element
are sort of the number of elements in
each list okay I thought I was going to
back my way into this that gives me a
way to merge things so here's what merge
sort would do merge sort takes this idea
of divide and conquer and it does the
following it says let's divide the list
in half there's the divide and conquer
and let's keep dividing each of those
lists in half until we get down to
something that's really easy to sort
what's the simplest thing to sort this
to size one right all right so continue
until we have singleton lists once I got
lists of size one they're sorted and
then combine them and combine them by
doing emerge the sub lists and again you
see that flavor I'm going to just keep
dividing it up until they get something
really easy and then I'm going to
combine and this is different than
binary search now the combine is going
to have to do some work so I've given
you a piece of code that does this and I
come back to it in a second but it's up
there but what I'd like to do is to try
and give you a sort of a little
simulation of how this would work and I
was going to originally make the TAS
come up here and do it but I don't have
enough TAS to do a full merge sort so
I'm hoping and I also have these really
high-tech props I spent tons and tons of
Dept money on them as you can see I hope
you can see this because I'm going to
try and simulate what a merge sort does
I've got eight things I want to sort
here and those initially start out here
at top level first step is divide them
in half
all right and I should have had a marker
here remember I need to come back there
not yet done
what do I do divide them in half again
okay you know if I had like shells and
peas here I could make some more money
right all right what do I do I divide
them in half one more time let me
cluster them because really what I have
sorry
separate them out I've gone from one
problem size eight down to eight
problems a size one at this stage I'm at
my singleton case so this is easy what
do I do I merge and the merge is put
them in order okay what do I do next
obvious thing I merge these and that as
we saw was a nice linear operation it's
fun to do it upside down and then one
more merge which is I take the smallest
elements of each one until I get to
where I want Wow aren't you impressed
okay no please don't clap not for that
one now let me do it a second time to
show you that that's why I'm saying this
poorly let me say it again that's the
general idea what was what should you
see out of that I just kept subdividing
down till they got really easy problems
and then I combined them back I actually
misled you slightly there or maybe a lot
because I did it in parallel in fact let
me just shuffle these up a little bit
really what's going to happen here
because this is a sequential computer is
that we're going to start off up here
yeah a top level we're going to divide
into half and then we're going to do the
complete subdivision and merge here
before we ever come back and do this one
right we're going to do a division here
and then a division there at that stage
we can merge these and then take this
down through the division merge and
bring them back whoops sorry about that
let's bring them back up
okay let me show you an example by
running that I've got a little list I've
made here called test
let's run mergesort on it and then we'll
look at the code okay
what I would like you to see is I've
been printing out as I went along
actually that's back up slightly and
look at the code there's mergesort takes
in a list what does it say to do it says
check to see if I'm in that base case
it's the list of less of length less
than two is it one basically in which
case just return a copy of the list okay
that's the simple case otherwise notice
what it says to do says find the
midpoint and split the list in half
right copy of the back end so I copy the
left-side copy of the right side run
merge sort on those by induction if it
does the right thing I'm going to get
back to lists and I'm going to then
merge them together and notice I'm going
to do I'm going to print here the list
if we go into it and a print of the
merge when we're done and then just
return that merge up here there's a
little more code there I'll let you just
rock it but you can see it's basically
doing what I did over there setting up
two indices for the two sub lists is
just walking down finding the smallest
element putting it into a new list when
it gets to the end of one of the lists
it skips to the next part and only one
of these two pieces will get called
because only one of them is going to
have things left over it's going to add
the other pieces in okay if you look at
that then let's look at what happened
when we ran this alright we started off
with a call with that list aha split it
in half it's going down the left side of
this that got split in half and that got
split in half until I got to a list of
size one here's the first list of size
one there's the second list of size one
so I merged them it's now in the right
order and that's coming from right there
having done that it goes back up and
picks the second sub list which Akane
Rattray shirts that came from there
right gets it down to base case merges
it when these two merges are done we're
basically at a stage in that branch
where we can now merge those two
together
which gives us that and it goes through
the rest of it okay a really nice
algorithm set as I said an example of
dividing conquer notice here that it's
different than the binary search case
we're certainly dividing down but the
combination now actually takes some work
right I have to actually figure out how
to put them back together and that's a
general thing you want to keep in mind
when you're thinking about designing a
dividing conquer kind of algorithm you
really want to get the power dividing
things up but if you end up doing a ton
of work at the combination stage you may
not have gained anything so you really
want to think about that trade-off all
right having said that what's the
complexity here
where there is a dumb question because
I've been telling you for the last two
lectures the complexities n log n but
let's see if it really is what's the
complexity here we think about it we
start off with a problem of size n what
do we do we split it into two problems
of size n over two those gets split each
into two problems of size n over four
and we keep doing that until we get down
to a level in this tree where we have
only Singleton's left over okay once
we're there we have to do the merge and
notice what happens here we said each of
the merge operations was of order n but
n is different right down here I've just
got two things to merge and then I've
got things of size two to merge and then
things of size four to merge but notice
a trade off I have n operations if you
like down there of size one up here I
have n over two operations of size two
up here I've got n over four operations
of size four so I always have to do a
merge of n elements how much time does
that take well we said it right
oops where did I put it right there
order em so I have order and operations
at each level in the tree and then how
many levels deep in mine well that's the
divide right so how many levels do I
have log in because it each stage on
cutting the problem in half so I start
off with then then it's n over 2 enter
before anyway so I got n so I have n
operations log n times there we go n log
n focus a long time to get there but
it's a nice algorithm to have all right
let me generalize this slightly ok when
we get a problem a standard tool to try
and attack it with is to say is there
some way to break this problem down into
simpler or shouldn't say simpler smaller
versions of the same problem ok if I can
do that it's a good candidate for divide
and conquer and then the things I have
to ask is how much of a division do I
want to do the obvious ones that divide
it in half but there may be cases where
there are different divisions you want
to have take place the second question I
want to ask is what's the base case when
do I get down to a problem small enough
that is basically trivial to solve here
it was lists of size 1 I could have
stopped at list of size 2 right that's
an easy comparison do one comparison and
return one of two possible orders on it
but I need to decide that the third
thing I need to decide is how do I
combine ok I'll point out to you in the
binary search case combination was
trivial right answer to the final search
was just the answer all the way up here
a little more work and that's why I'll
come back to that idea if I'm basically
just squeezing jello that is I'm trying
to make the problem simpler but the
combination turns out to be really
complex
I've not gained anything so things that
are good candidates for divide and
conquer are problems where it's easy to
figure out how to divide down and the
combination is of a low complexity be
nice if it was less than linear but
linear is nice because then I'm going to
get that
and login kind of behavior and if you
ask the TAS and recitation tomorrow
they'll tell you that you see a lot of n
log n algorithms in computer science
it's a very common class of algorithm
and it's a very useful one to have okay
now one of the questions we could still
ask is right we got binary search which
is got this nice log behavior only if we
can sort things you know we get this
this n log n behavior and we got an N
log n behavior overall but can we
actually do better in terms of searching
I'm going to show you one last technique
in fact we're put quotes around the word
better but it does better than even this
kind of binary search and that's a
method called hashing ok we've actually
seen hashing you just don't know hashing
is the technique that's used in Python
to represent dictionaries hashing is
used when you actually come in to Logan
Airport in immigration or Homeland
Security checks your picture against a
database hashing is used every time you
enter a password into a system so what
in the world is hashing let me start
with a simple little example suppose I
want to represent a collection of
integers which is a really easy little
example and I promise you that the
integers are never going to be anything
other than between the range of 0 to 9
ok so it might be the collection 1 and 5
it might be 2 3 4 8 I mean some
collection of integers but I guarantee
you it's between 0 & 9
here's the trick I can play I can build
I can't count I could build a list with
spots for all of those elements zero one
two three four five six seven eight nine
and then when I want to create my set I
could simply put a 1 everywhere that
that integer falls so if I wanted to
represent this for example this is the
set two six and eight I put a 1 in those
slots alright this seems a little weird
but bear with me for a second in fact
I've given you a little piece of code to
do it which is the next piece of code on
on the handout so let's take a look at
it for a second alright this little set
of code here from create insert and
member what's create do it says given a
low and a high range in this case would
be 0 tonight I'm going to build ah a
list right you can see that little loop
through going through there what am i
doing on creating a list with just that
special symbol none in it so I'm
building the list I'm returning that as
my set and then to create the object
I'll simply do a set of inserts if I
want the values 2 6 & 8 in there I would
do an insert of 2 into that set and sort
of 6 into that set and an insert of 8
into that set and what does it do it
marks a 1 in each of those spots now
what did I want to do I wanted to check
membership I want to do search well
that's simple given that representation
and some value I just say gee is it
there what's the order complexity here
I know I Drive you nuts asking questions
what's the order complexity here
quadratic linear log constant any takers
I don't have the wrong glasses on to see
hands up to but who said it constant why
yeah
thank you all right it is constant you
keep sitting back there where I can't
get to you thank you very much why is it
constant remember we said we designed
lists so that the access no matter where
it was in the list was constant time
that is another way of saying that
looking up this thing here is constant
so this is constant time order one okay
come on you know representing sets of
integers this is pretty dumb suppose I
want to have a set of characters how
could I do that well the idea of a hash
like what's called a hash function is to
have some way of mapping any kind of
data into integers so let's look at the
second example all right keep doing that
this piece of code from here to here
gives me a way of now creating a hash
table of size 256 Ord is a built-in
Python representation there's lots of
them around it takes any character and
gives you back an integer in fact is to
show that to you if I go down here and I
type or D
sorry I did that wrong let me try again
get two exceptions in a second I give it
some character it gives me back an
integer representing it looks weird why
is three come back to some other thing
that's the internal representation that
Python uses for this if I give it some
other character now would help if I
could type and give it some other
character it gives me back a
representation so now here's the idea I
build a list 256 elements long right and
I fill it up with those special
characters none
that's what create is going to do right
here and then hash character takes in
any string or character single character
gives you back a number and notice what
I do if I want to create a set or a
sequence representing these things I
simply insert into that list that goes
through and puts ones in the right place
and then if I want to find out ever
something's there I do the same thing
but notice now hash is converting the
input into an integer okay so what's the
idea if I know what my hash function
does it maps in this case characters
into a range 0 to 256 0 to 255 I create
a list that long and I simply mark
things and my lookup is still constant
alright characters are simple suppose
you want to represent sets of strings
well you basically just generalize the
hash function I think one of the classic
ones for Strings is called the raven
carp algorithm and it's simply the same
idea that you have a mapping from your
input into a set of integers Wow ok
maybe not so well but this is now
constant alright this is constant time
access so I can do searching in constant
time which is great
where's the penalty what did I trade off
here well I want to suggest that what I
did was I really traded
space or time makes me sound like an
astrophysicist somehow right what do I
mean by that I have constant time access
which is great but I paid a price which
is I had to use up some space in the
case of integers it was easy in the case
of character so I have to give up a list
of 256 no big deal
imagine how you want to do faces alright
you got a picture of somebody's face
some million pixels each pixel has a
range of values from 0 to 256
I want to hash a face with some function
into an integer ok I may not want to do
the full range of this but I may decide
I have to use a lot of gigabytes of
space in order to do the trade-off and
the reason I'm showing you this is that
this is a gain a common trade-off in
computer science that in many cases I
can gain efficiency if I'm willing to
give up space having said that though
there's may still be a problem or there
ought to be a problem that may be
bugging you slightly which is how do I
guarantee that my hash function takes
any input into exactly one spot in the
storage space the answer is I can't okay
in the simple case of integers I can but
in the case of something more complex
like faces or fingerprints or passwords
for that matter it's hard to design a
hash function that has completely even
distribution meaning that it takes any
input into exactly one output spot so
what you typically do in a hash case is
you design your code to deal with that
you try and design which I'm going to
come back to then so can you try and use
a hash function that spreads things out
pretty evenly but the places you store
into and those lists may have to
themselves have a small list in there
and when you go to check something you
may have to do a linear search through
the elements in that list the good news
is the elements in any one spot in a
hash table are likely to be a small
number three four five so the search is
really easy you're not searching a
million things you're searching three or
four things but nonetheless you have to
do that trade-off the last thing I want
to say about hashes are
they're actually really hard to create
there's been a lot of work done on these
over the years but in fact it's pretty
hard to invent a good hash function so
my advice to you is if you want to use
something with a hash go to a library
look up a good hash function game for
Strings there's a classic set of them
that work pretty well for integers
there's some real simple ones if there's
something more complex find a good hash
function but designing a really good
hash function takes a lot of effort
because you want it to have that even
distribution you'd like it to have as
few duplicates if you like in each spot
in the hash table for each one of the
things that you use okay let me pull
back for a second there what have we
done over the last three or four
lectures we've started introducing you
to classes of algorithms things that I'd
like you to be able to see are how to do
some simple complexity analysis perhaps
more importantly how to recognize a kind
of algorithm based on its properties and
know what class it belongs to this is a
hint if you like leading towards the
next quiz that you ought to be able to
say that looks like a logarithmic
algorithm because it's got a particular
property
it looks like an N log n algorithm
because it has a particular property and
the third thing we've done is we've
given you now a set of sort of standard
algorithms if you like brute force let's
walk through every possible case I works
well if the problem sizes are small
we've had a number of variants of guess
and check or hypothesize and test where
you try and guess the solution and then
check it and use that to refine your
search successive approximation
newton-raphson was one nice example but
there's a whole class of things that get
closer and closer reducing your error as
you go along
divide and conquer right and actually I
guess in between there bisection which
is really just a variant of successive
approximation but divide and conquer is
a class of algorithm these are tools you
want your toolbox these are the kinds of
algorithms that you should be able to
recognize and what I'd like you to begin
to do is to look at a problem and say
gee which kind of algorithm is most
likely to be successful on this problem
and
now fit into that case okay starting
next don't worry I'm not going to quit
36 minutes after I got one more topic
for today but jumping ahead I'm going to
skip in a second now to talk about one
last linguistic thing from from Python
but I want to preface professor Guttag
is going to pick up next week and what
we want to start doing then is taking
these classes of algorithms and start
looking at much more complex algorithms
things you're more likely to use in
problems things like knapsack problem
knapsack problems as we move ahead but
the tools you've seen so far really the
things that we're going to see as we
build those algorithms okay
I want to spend the last portion of this
lecture doing one last piece of
linguistic stuff one last little thing
from Python and that's to talk about
exceptions okay you've actually seen
exceptions a lot you just didn't know
that's what they were because exceptions
show up everywhere in Python and let me
give you a couple of examples you clear
some space here if I type in that
expression I get an error right this is
not defined but in fact what this did
was it threw an exception in the
exceptions and ain't a called a name
error exception it says you gave me
something I didn't know how to deal with
I'm going to throw it or raise it to use
the right term to somebody in case they
can handle it but it's a particular kind
of exception I might do something like I
remind you I had test if I do this try
and get the tenth element of a list it's
only eight long I get what looks like an
error but it's actually throwing an
exception and the exceptions right there
it says it's an index error that is it's
trying to do something going beyond the
range of what this thing could deal with
okay you say come on I've seen these all
the time every time I type something
into my program it does one of these
things right when we're just interacting
with idle with the interactive editor or
sorry the interactive environment if you
like that's what you expect what's
happening is that we're typing in
something on expression it doesn't know
how to deal with its raising the
exception but it is simply bubbling up
to the top
level saying you've got a problem samosa
at in a long day suppose instead you're
in the middle of some deep piece of code
and you get one of these cases it's kind
of annoying if it throws it all the way
back up to top level for you to fix if
it's truly a bug that's the right thing
to do you want to catch it but in many
cases exceptions are things that in fact
you as a program designer could have
handled so I'm going to distinguish in
fact between unhandled exceptions which
are the things that we saw there and
handled exceptions I'm going to show you
in a second how to handle them but let's
look at an example what do I mean by a
handled exception well let's look at the
next piece of code okay it's right here
it's called read float look at it in a
second but let me start to set the stage
up for this suppose I want to input or
sorry I want you as a user to input a
floating-point number all right we
talked about things you could do to try
and make sure that happens
you can run through a little loop to say
keep trying until you get one but one of
the ways I could deal with it is what's
shown here unless this little loop say
to do so the loop says whoops wrong one
this little loop says I'm going to write
a function or procedure that takes in
two messages I'm going to run through a
loop and I'm going to request some input
which I'm going to read in with with raw
input and store that into Val and this
as you might expect I'm going to then
try and see if I can convert that into a
float oh wait a minute that's a little
different than what we did last time
right last time we checked the type and
said if it is a float you're okay if not
carry on in this case what would happen
well float is going to try and do the
coercion it's going to try and turn it
into a floating-point number if it does
I'm great right and I like just to
return Val if it doesn't floats going to
throw or raise to use the right term and
exception it's going to say something
like a type error factor let's try it
over here all right if I go over here
and I say float of three it's going to
do the conversion but if I say turn this
into a float ah throws a value error
exception says it's wrong kind of value
that I've got
so I'm going to write a little piece of
code that says if it gives me a float
I'm set but if not I'd like to have the
code handle the exception and that's
what this funky try/except thing does
okay this is a try except block and
here's the flow of control that takes
place in there when I hit a try block
it's going to literally do that it's
going to try and execute the
instructions if it can successfully
execute the instructions it is going to
skip past the except block and just
carry on with the rest of the code if
however it raises an exception that
exception at least in this case where
it's a pure except with no tags on it is
going to get if you like thrown directly
to the except block and it's going to
try and execute that so notice what's
going to happen here then if I give it
something that can be turned into a
float I come in here I read the
inputting that if it can be turned into
a float I'm going to just return the
value and I'm set if not it's basically
going to throw it to this point in which
case I'm going to print out an error
message and oh yeah I'm still in that
while loop so it's going to go around so
in fact if I go here and in the
uncomment this and run the code it says
enter a float and if I give it something
that can be sorry I've got a yes never
mind the grades crap where did I have
that let me comment that out somehow
it's appropriate in the middle of my
lecture for it to say whoops at me but
wasn't what I intended and we will try
this again okay so is enter a float I
give it something that can be converted
into a float it's just fine let me go
back and run it again though if I run it
again it says enter a float
aha it goes into that accept portion
prints out a message and goes back
around the while loop to say try again
and it's going to keep doing this until
I give it something that does serve as a
float right so an exception then has
this format that I can control as a
programmer why would I want to use this
well some things I can actually expect
may happen and I want to handle them the
float examples are simple and I'm going
to generalize in a second here's a
better example I'm writing a piece of
code that wants to input a file and I
can certainly imagine something that
says give me the file name I'm going to
do something with it I can't guarantee
that the file may exist under that name
but I know that's something that might
occur so a nice way to handle it is to
write it as an exception that says
here's what I want to do if I get the
file but just in case the file name is
not there here's what I want to do in
that case to handle it let me specify
what the exception should do all right
in the example I just wrote here this is
pretty trivial right ok I'm trying to
input floats I could generalize this
pretty nicely imagine the same kind of
idea where I want to simply say I want
to take input of anything and try and
see how to make sure I get the right
kind of thing I want to make it
polymorphic well that's pretty easy to
do that is basically the next example
right here okay let me comment this one
out I can do exactly the same kind of
thing all right well now what I'm going
to try and do is read in a set of values
where I'm going to give up a type of
value as well as the messages formats
the same I'm going to ask for some input
and then I'm going to use that procedure
to check is this the right type of value
I'm going to try and use that to do the
coercion if you like same thing if it
works I'm going to skip that if it not
is going to throw the exception why is
this nice well that's a handy piece of
code right because imagine I've got that
down I can now store that away in some
file name input top py and import it
into every one of my procedure functions
sorry my files of procedures because
it's a standard way of not giving me the
input ok so far though I've just shown
you what
happens inside a piece of code it raises
an exception it goes to that except
Clause we don't have to use it just
inside of one place we can actually use
it more generally and that gets me to
the last example I wanted to show you
and let me uncomment this let's take a
look at this code this looks like a
handy piece of code to have given what
we just recently did to you all right
get grades so the function that's going
to say give me a file name and I'm going
to go off and open that up and bind it
to a local variable and if it's
successful then I just like to go off
and do some things like turn it into a
list so I can compute average score or
distributions or something else I don't
really care what's going on in here
notice though what I've done open if it
doesn't succeed is going to raise a
particular kind of exception called IO
error and so I've done a little bit
different thing here which is I've put
the accept part of the block with IO
error what does that say it says if in
the code up here I get an exception of
that sort I'm going to go to this place
to handle it
on the other hand if I'm inside this
procedure and some other exception is
raised
that's not tagged by that one it's going
to raise it up the chain if that
procedure was called by some other
procedures going to say is there an
exception block in there that can handle
that if not I'm going to keep going up
the chain until eventually I get to the
top level and you can see that down here
I'm going to run this in a sacrament
this is just a piece of code where I'm
going to say gee if I can get the grades
do something if not carry on right and
if I go ahead and run this now it's
going to say whoops at me okay what
happened I'm down here and try I'm
trying to do get grades which is a call
to that function which is not bound to
my in my in my yeah in my computer that
says it's in here it's in this try block
it raised an exception but it wasn't an
i/o error so it passes it back past this
exception up to this level which gets to
that exception
so let me say this a little bit better
than I can write exceptions inside a
piece of code try this if it doesn't
work I can have an exception that
catches any error at that level or I can
say catch only these kinds of errors at
that level otherwise pass them up the
chain and that exception will keep
getting passed up the chain of calls
until it either gets to top level in
which case it looks like what you see
all the time looks like an error but it
tells you what the error came from or it
gets an exception handler that can deal
with it okay so the last thing to say
about this is what's the difference
between an exception and an assert all
right we introduced asserts earlier on
you've actually seen them in some pieces
of code so what's the difference between
the two of them well here's my way of
describing it the goal of an assert or
an assert statement is basically to say
look you can be sure that my function is
going to give this kind of result if you
give me inputs of a particular type
sorry wrong way saying if you give me
inputs that satisfy some particular
constraints right that was the kind of
thing you saw assert said here are some
conditions to test if they're true I'm
going to let the rest of the code run if
not I'm going to throw an error alright
so the assertion is basically saying we
got some preconditions those are the
clauses inside the assert that have to
be true and there's a post condition and
in essence what the assert is saying is
or rather the programmer saying using
these Surtees if you give me input that
satisfies the preconditions I'm
guaranteeing to you that my code is
going to give you something that meets
the post condition it's going to do the
right thing and as a consequence as you
saw with the asserts if the
preconditions aren't true it throws an
error it goes back up the top level
saying stops operation immediately and
goes back up the top level okay
asserts in fact are nice in the sense
that they let you check conditions at
debugging time or testing time so you
can actually use them to see where your
code is going an exception when you use
an exception basically what you're
saying is look you can do anything you
want with my function and you can be
sure that I'm going to tell you if
something is going wrong and in many
cases I'm going to handle it myself
so as much as possible the exceptions
are going to try and handle unexpected
things actually wrong term you expected
them but not what the user did it's
going to try and handle conditions other
than the normal ones itself so you can
use the thing in any way if a cat is
going to try and throw it to somebody
else to handle and only if there is no
handler for that unexpected condition
will it come up to top level so
summarizing better assert is something
you put in to say to the user make sure
you're giving me input of this type but
I'm going to guarantee you the rest of
the code works correctly exceptions and
exception handlers are saying here are
the odd cases that I might see and
here's what I'd like to do in those
cases in order to try and be able to
deal with them last thing to say is why
would you want to have exceptions well
let's go back to that case of inputting
a simple little floating point if I'm
expecting mostly numbers in I can
certainly try and do the coercion I
could have done that just doing the
coercion right the problem is I want to
know if in fact I've got something
that's not of the form I expect I'm much
better having an exception get handled
at the time of input tend to let that
property that value rather propagate
through a whole bunch of code until
eventually hits an error 17 calls later
and you have no clue where it came from
so the exceptions are useful when you
want to have the ability to say I expect
in general this kind of behavior but I
do know there are some other things that
might happen and here's what I'd like to
do in each one of those cases but I do
want to make sure that I don't let a
value that I'm not expecting pass
through that goes back to that idea of
sort of discipline coding it's easy to
have assumptions about what you think
are going to come into the program when
you write it if you really know what
they are using assert but if you think
there's going to be some flexibility you
want to prevent
the user getting trapped in the bad spot
and exceptions as a consequence or a
good thing to use